Guide to the Simon W. and Sophie Gerson Papers TAM 330
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Simon W. and Sophie Gerson Papers
1925-2001
1945-1991
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hard, Robert
TAM 330
15 Linear Feet in 30 manuscript boxes, 1 record carton, 1 flat box and 1 oversize folder in a shared flat box.
Simon W. (Si) Gerson, 1909-2004, was the longtime New York State, and later national legislative/political action director for the Communist Party, and was an advocate of proportional representation and ballot access for minor political parties, including in the 1980s-90s as a leader of the Coalition for Free and Open Elections (COFOE). He served as Confidential Examiner to Manhattan Borough President Stanley M. Isaacs, 1938-40, managed Communist election campaigns (later writing a biography Pete: The Story of Peter V. Cacchione, New York's First Communist Councilman), and organized activities in support of the Communist Party leaders indicted under the Smith Act, as was Gerson. In the 1950s he was executive editor of the Party's newspaper, the Daily Worker, and of its later successor, the Daily World. Along with his wife, Sophie Melvin Gerson, an organizer of the Gastonia Textile Strike of 1929, he was a longtime resident of and community activist in the Bensonhurst neighborhood in Brooklyn, New York. The papers contain clippings, correspondence with leading communists and political figures, published and unpublished writings including manuscripts, memorandums, newspaper columns, reviews and reports, a scrapbook and speeches, including materials relating to Cacchione's career and death, and to Gerson's several campaigns for public office, research notes and typescript drafts for several chapters of a never-completed book, "Do We Really Have Free Elections (ca. 1990)," a related manuscript by Adam Lapin, "Tweedledum and Tweedledee: The American Two Party System," Communist Party internal documents, including reports by leading figures, many relating to the communist political crises of 1956-58 and 1989-91, and minutes of and correspondence relating to COFOE and the publication Ballot Access News.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Deborah Gerson in 2005; additional materials were donated by Robert Hard and Sarah Steiner in 2011. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2005.009, 2005.011, NPA.2005.225, 2011.043, and 2011.080.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically, except for boxes 27-31, which have not been arranged by an archivist. The collection is arranged into five series:
Series I: Papers, 1927-2001
Series II: Scrapbooks, undated
Series III: Photographs, 1927-1991
Series IV: Addendum, 1918-1947
Series V: Addendum 2011, undated
The collection is organized into four series: I, Papers; II, Addendum; Scrapbook; III, Addendum; IV, Addendum, 2011. Each is arranged alphabetically, and the contents of each folder are arranged chronologically, except for boxes 27-31, which are unprocessed.
Historical/Biographical Note
Simon W. (Si) Gerson, 1909-2004, was the longtime New York State, and later national legislative/political action director for the Communist Party, and was an advocate of proportional representation and ballot access for minor political parties, including in the 1980s-90s as a leader of the Coalition for Free and Open Elections (COFOE). He served as Confidential Examiner to Manhattan Borough President Stanley M. Isaacs, 1938-40, until controversy over his Party membership caused him to resign this position, managed Communist election campaigns (later writing a biography Pete: The Story of Peter V. Cacchione, New York's First Communist Councilman), unsuccessfully campaigning to succeed Cacchione after his death in 1947, and organized activities in support of the Communist Party leaders indicted under the Smith Act, as was Gerson. In the 1950s he was executive editor of the Party's newspaper, the Daily Worker, and of its later successor, the Daily World. Along with his wife, Sophie Melvin Gerson, an organizer of the Gastonia Textile Strike of 1929, he was a longtime resident of and community activist in the Bensonhurst neighborhood in Brooklyn, New York.
Simon W. Gerson Selected Bibliography: Monographs and articles in periodicals (excluding book reviews and newspaper articles):
------, "A People's' Constitution for New York." New York State Communist Party, n.d.
"The New Left Social Fascism." Communist, 9 (July, 1930): 622-631.
It Is Happening Here. New York: New York State Committee, Communist Party, 1941.
Public Speaking: A Speakers Guide Book, by Peter V. Cacchione; foreword by Simon W. Gerson. New York: Workers Library Publishers, 1942.
"Thomas E. Dewey: His Record." Communist 22 (May, 1943): 461-468.
Pete Cacchione--His Record. New York: Workers Library, 1943.
"The Stork Club Goes for Dewey." New Masses 60, no. 11 (Sep 11, 1946): 17-20.
"How You Can Beat Dewey." New Masses 61, no. 6 (November 5, 1946): 4-5.
"Electoral Coalition Problems." Political Affairs, 26 (October, 1947): 894-901.
"La Guardia: Guerrilla Warrior." New Masses (October 7, 1947): 9-12.
The Killing of William Milton, by Art Shields, Introduction by Simon W. Gerson. New York: Daily Worker, 1948.
Either the Constitution or the Mundt Bill: America Can't Have Both. New York: New Century, 1950.
"The Jury System and Democratic Rights." Political Affairs, 31: 35-44 (July, 1952).
The Outlook for the N.Y. City Elections. New York State Communist Party (1954).
The Rights You Save May Be Your Own. New York: New York State Communist Party, 1954.
"A Communist at Cornell." Masses & Mainstream, 8 (July, 1955): 28-35.
Pete: The Story of Peter V. Cacchione, New York's First Communist Councilman. New York: International Publishers, 1976.
"On Building a Mass Anti-monopoly Party." Political Affairs (October 1977): 22-26.
After Fifty Years: Revisiting the U.S.S.R. New York: NWR Publications, 1978.
"The 1978 Midterm Elections." Political Affairs 57, no.1 (January, 1978): 18-21.
"Vito Marcantonio: From Republican to Radical." Political Affairs (November, 1979)
"Independence and Coalition; The Communist View." Political Affairs (December, 1979): 7-12.
"From Truman Doctrine to Reagan Doctrine." Political Affairs (August, 1987): 15-21.
"How to Win Political Democracy." Political Affairs (November, 1985): 14-17.
"Does the U.S. Have Free Elections?" Political Affairs (December, 1990): 10-14.
"Again, on Political Independence." Si Gerson and Jarvis Tyner. Political Affairs (January, 1993): 41.
Related Materials
Peter V. Cacchione Papers (TAM 073)
Michael Gold: Peter V. Cacchione Manuscripts (TAM 339)
Simon W. Gerson Audiocassettes (OH 054)
Sophie M. Gerson Letters to Simon W. Gerson (TAM 401)
Stanley M. Isaacs Papers, New York Public Library (MssCol 1526)
Scope and Content Note
The papers contain clippings, correspondence with leading communists and political figures, published and unpublished writings including manuscripts, memorandums, newspaper columns, reviews and reports, a scrapbook and speeches, including materials relating to Cacchione's career and death, and to Gerson's several campaigns for public office (including a speech recorded on two phonograph discs), research notes and typescript drafts for several chapters of a never-completed book, "Do We Really Have Free Elections (ca. 1990)," a related manuscript by Adam Lapin, "Tweedledum and Tweedledee: The American Two Party System," Communist Party internal documents, including reports by leading figures, many relating to the communist political crises of 1956-58 and 1989-91, minutes of and correspondence relating to Coalition for Free and Open Elections (COFOE) and the publication Ballot Access News, clippings relating to Sophie Gerson's activities in Gastonia, North Carolina during the 1929 textile strike there, and audiocassettes and reel to reel tapes (public programs honoring the Gersons, and Gus Hall "Updates").
Notable individuals represented include: Ann Rosenhaft and Richard Winger (COFOE), Irving Adler, Helen Alfred (Peace Publications), Zaccariah Chafee, Mike Davidow, William O. Douglas, Harry Eisman, Fred Fine, William Z. Foster, Gil Green, Dorothy Healey, Murray Kempton, James Jackson, Al Lannon, Robert Minor, George Morris, Otto Nathan, Joseph North, John Pittman, Al Richmond, Lester Rodney, Morton Sobell, Norman Thomas, Robert Thompson, Carl Winter, and Alden Whitman (New York Times).
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Material
Three manuscripts by Mike Gold have been separated to the Michael Gold: Peter V. Cacchione Manuscripts (TAM 339). Approximately 30 audiocassettes (1980s) that include "Gus Hall Updates" and several interviews with Simon Gerson have been separated to the Simon W. Gerson Audiocassettes (OH 054).
Representative government and representation |z United States.; Audiocassettes.; Politics, Practical |z New York (State) |z New York.; Audiotapes.; Proportional representation.; Sound recordings.; Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government |y 20th century.; Third parties (United States politics); Trials (Political crimes and offenses) -- United States.; Photographs.; Communist Trial, New York, N.Y., 1949.; Elections -- New York (State) -- New York.; Communist trials -- United States.; Minorities |x Suffrage |z United States.; Minorities |x Suffrage |z New York (State); Political parties |z New York (State).; Communism -- New York (State) -- New York; Election law |z New York (State); Communists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Journalism, Communist -- United States.; Briefs (legal documents); Ballots.; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; Communists -- United States.; Proportional representation |z New York (State); Jewish communists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Transcripts.; Fliers (printed matter); Testimonies.; Speeches.; Clippings (information artifacts); Scrapbooks.; Manuscripts (document genre); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Reports.; Resolutions (administrative records); Petitions.; Press releases.; Memorandums.; Notes.; Communism -- United States.; Minutes (administrative records); Fine, Fred.; Davidow, Mike; Chafee, Zechariah, 1885-1957; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Cacchione, Peter V., 1897-1947; Bransten, Richard, 1906-1955; Alfred, Helen L.; Gerson, Simon W.; Thompson, Robert George, 1915-1966.; Civil Rights Congress (U.S.); Sobell, Morton; Rosenhaft, Ann.; Richmond, Al, 1913-1987.; Rodney, Lester, 1911-; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961.; Lannon, Al, 1907-1969; Kempton, Murray, 1917-; Minor, Robert, 1884-1952; McKenney, Ruth, 1911-1972; North, Joseph; Aizman, Garri.; Gerson, Sophie; Winger, Richard; Green, Gil, 1906-; Isaacs, Stanley M. (Stanley Myer), 1882-1962; Lapin, Adam. Tweedledum and tweedledee: the American two party system.; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980; Adler, Irving; Winter, Carl, 1906-1991; Jackson, James E., 1914-2007; Healey, Dorothy, 1914-2006; Nathan, Otto, 1893-1987.; People's weekly world (New York, N.Y.); Daily World (New York, N.Y.); Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Whitman, Alden; American Labor Party of the State of New York; Pittman, John; Center for Voting and Democracy; Coalition for Free and Open Elections (U.S.); Communist Party of the United States of America. Convention (16th: 1957: New York); Communist Party of the United States of America. Convention (25th: 1991: Cleveland); Communist Party of the United States of America; Daily Worker (New York); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.). Office of the President; New York (N.Y.). City Council--Elections; Communist Party of the United States of America (New York); Peace Publications Committee; Ballot Access News; Gerson, Deborah; Hard, Robert; Steiner, Sarah
- Series I: Papers, 1927-2001
  - Abt, John: Notes on the First Amendment, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Activities of Anti-Semitic Groups in New York City [A Report to the Mayor, From Nathan Frankel and Byrnes MacDonald], Jul 18, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Labor Party New York (City and State), 1938-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Student Delegation to Russia, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aptheker, Herbert "Democracy, Diversity, and Property", Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Association of City Hall Reporters/The Inner Circle, 1948, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ballot Access News, 1983-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bath Beach Community Improvement Association (Brooklyn, NY), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bay View Civic Association (Brooklyn, NY), Undated, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bensonhurst Fraternal Society (Brooklyn, NY), Undated, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bill of Rights Conference (New York, NY), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Budget, Personal, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cacchione, Peter V.: "Builders of America" (Play Written for the International Workers Order), Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cacchione, Peter V.: City Council Career, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cacchione, Peter V.: Death, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cacchione, Peter V.: Election Campaigns, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cacchione, Peter V.: Election Campaign, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cacchione, Peter V.: Election Campaign, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cacchione, Peter V.: Pamphlets, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cacchione, Peter V.: Succession Fight, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Celler, Emmanuel [Congressman Brooklyn, NY 12th District], Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Center for Voting and Democracy, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Citizens Committee for the Election of Elizabeth Gurley Flynn to Congress (Bronx, NY), Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Citizens Emergency Defense Committee (re Smith Act Defendants ), 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - City Council Campaign, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - City Council Campaign: Bay Ridge Incident (Violence), 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - City Council Campaign: Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - City Council Campaign: Literature, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - City Council Campaign: Loudspeaker Bill (Local), 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - City Council Campaign: Norman Mailer Support Statement, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - City Council Campaign: Press Releases, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - City Council Campaign: Press Releases, Speeches by Others in Support of Gerson, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - City Council Campaign: Sanford Chalfin Case (Police Brutality), 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - City Council Campaign: Radio Schedule, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - City Council Campaign: Scrapbook, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - City Council Campaign: Speech Gentleman's Agreement and Franco, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - City Council Campaign: Speeches on Israel, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - City Council Campaign: Speech "La Guardia vs O'Dwyer", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - City Council Campaign: Speech "Liberal Party and Berle", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - City Council Campaign: Speech "O'Dwyer Record on Civil Liberties", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - City Council Campaign: Speech "Registration and Wasted Vote", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - City Council Campaign: Speech "Robert Thompson Attack and O'Dwyer Record on Civil Liberties", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - City Council Campaign Speech: "Trial of Eleven (CP Smith Activities)", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - City Council Campaign: Three Minute [Sound] Recording Typescript, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Civil Rights Congress Bail Fund, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Coalition for Free and Open Elections (COFOE), 1986-1996, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - COFOE Amicus Brief (Miller v. Lorain County, Ohio), 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - COFOE Correspondence, 1985-1997 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - COFOE Minutes, 1987-1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Commission on Fair Elections, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Committee for Independent Political Action (Includes: "Dialogue with James Weinstein"), 1966 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Committee of Neighbors and Friends of Si Gerson (re Smith Act indictment), 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Communist Party New York: Municipal/State Political Action, Politics, 1953-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Communist Party New York State: Election Campaign and Ballot Fight, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Communist Party New York State: MTA Fare Increase, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Communist Party New York State: Save the 5 Cents Fare Campaign, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Clippings (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Convention, 16th (New York, NY: Feb. 9-12, 1957), 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Correspondence Contents: Foster to Dennis 5/31; Ford to Gerson 6/15) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Correspondence, Documents, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Documents (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Documents, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Documents (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Documents, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Documents: California, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Documents: "New Features of the Negro Question in the United States" by James E. Jackson, Sep 1958 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Documents: "The Party Crisis and the Way Out" by William Z. Foster (reply to Bittelman), Dec 1957 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Documents: Program Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis of 1956-1958: Documents: "The Welfare State and the American Road to Socialism" by Alexander Bittelmen, Dec 1957 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Convention (25th Cleveland, Ohio, Dec. 5-8 1991) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents, Jan 1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents, Feb 1991-Jul 1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents, Aug 1991-Oct 1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents, Nov 1991-Dec 1991 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents: Memo on the Rachel Friedberg Estate, Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Communist Party Crisis of 1989-1991: Documents: Elders Committee, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Communist Party USA: Czechoslovakia Controversy (Gil Green, Dorothy Healey), 1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Communist Party USA: Dissent (Gil Green, Don Hammerquist), 1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Communist Party USA: Documents, 1993-1998 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Communist Party USA: Documents, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Communist Party USA: Documents Miscellaneous, 1940s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Communist Party USA: Hall-Tyner Campaign Committee Case, 1976-1992 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Communist Party USA: Jewish Question: Expulsion of Paul Novick, 1966-1973 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Confidential Examiner for Stanley M. Isaacs: Clippings, 1937-1939 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Confidential Examiner for Stanley M. Isaacs: Correspondence, Documents, 1937-1940 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Confidential Examiner for Stanley M. Isaacs: Correspondence and Statement, 1934-1939 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Confidential Examiner for Stanley M. Isaacs: Legal Documents, 1938-1940 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Confidential Examiner for Stanley M. Isaacs: McNaboe Investigation, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Confidential Examiner for Stanley M. Isaacs: Opposition, 1934-1939 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Confidential Examiner for Stanley M. Isaacs: Resignation, Sep 1940 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Confidential Examiner for Stanley M. Isaacs: Speech, Feb 16, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Confidential Examiner for Stanley M. Isaacs: Support, 1937-1938 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Congressional Campaign (13th District: Brooklyn, NY), 1952 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence; Aronson, James, 1963-1980 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Auerbach, Arnold Jerry, 1930s, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: First name only, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Abt, John, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Baker, William and Christina (Maine), 1987-1996 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Bransten, Richard and Ruth McKenney, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: California (Includes Dorthy Healey, Al Lannon, Mickey Lima, Lester Rodney), 1958-1996 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Cards, 1980-1998 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Cahfee, Zeccariah, 1,955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Davidow, Mike, 1975-1996 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Eisman, Harry, 1975, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley, Nov 10, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Foreign: Bulgaria, Hungary, Romania, 1964-1989 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Foreign: Denmark, 1970-1975, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Fine, Fred M., 1958-1964 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Garlin, Sender, 1974-1980 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Garlin, Sender, 1981-1992 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Green, Gil and Lillian, 1960-1965 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Hassman, Harry and Regina, 1988-1990 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Isaacs, Stanley M., 1938-1954 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Isaacs, Stanley M. (re Robert Thompson, etc.), 1955-1965, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Kra, Sabina, 1973, 1978-1985 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Magil, Abe, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Morris, George and Helen, 1972-1994 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: National Guardian, 1965, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: National Writers Union, 1989-1995 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Novosti Press Agency, 1975-1982 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: O'Dwyer, Paul, 1947, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Parenti, Michael, 1985-1995 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Peace Publications (Helen Alfred, editor), 1958 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Pittman, John and Margret, 1967-1992 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (re: Progressive), 1955 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Reese, Mark (re Jackie Robinson documentary), 1996, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Rubin, Danny, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Sobell, Morton and Helen, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Thomas Norman (re Smith Act, Fleischman bio of Norman Thomas; Robert Thompson, Herbert Aptheker Congressional Race, 1956-1966 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Volga Peace Cruise, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Whitman, Alden (New York Times reporter), 1978-1986 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Wheeler, Tim (re his nomination for James Aronson Award), 1990, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Winger, Richard, 1986-1992 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Winger, Richard, 1992-2001 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Winter, Carl and Helen, 1961, 1966, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 18)